Guys, Shandi, welcome back. And today in
Kafka part, we are going to set up the
Kafka cluster. Okay. So, if you have not
seen the
architecture video of Kafka then I would
highly recommend kindly check it out
first because all the fundamentals will
get clear from there and this is the
diagram from that uh architecture part
only. So today we would be doing a setup
of a Kafka cluster where we have have
two brokers and two controllers. Okay.
And then we will also set up a topic
with partition. So this is we going to
set up today.
So let's start without wasting any time.
So step one we need to download the
binary of latest Kafka version. So
generally there are two ways. One is if
you are using docker you can make use of
kafka docker image but since I have not
covered the docker part so I am going
with this one. Okay. We will download
the binary of kafka itself. Okay. And
also I would say that initially go with
this because many things will get clear.
You would see the package your own
right. So things will get little bit
more clear and docker once this is clear
docker is nothing okay so let's download
the binary of latest kafka version so
go to this link okay and here I have
picked the latest one 4.2.0
pick the binary download okay once it
get downloaded so you can check your
folder so kafka 4.2.0 zero you will see
all these subfolders will come.
Okay.
So this is the step one once downloaded
you will see below subfolders within
Kafka bin config all these things should
have come.
Now step two under each subfolder we
need to understand each subfolder. So
let's say first is bin. So if you open
the bin you will see. So here if you see
if you open the bin there are so many
script. Okay. So these you can say that
we can run it. These are executable
script. So let's say uh you want to
control certain Kafka component like
controller like broker you can run a
specific script itself. Okay. So this
folder contain executable shell script
which is used to perform tasks like you
can start the controller server, broker
server, you can create topic, delete
topic, publish message, consume message.
So you can say that it is just a wrapper
around
Kafka
Java API. I would say that okay so these
are just a wrapper.
So these scripts are wrapper around
Kafka internal Java API so that we can
run and manage Kafka components from CLI
itself. So from command line we can run
let's say producer.sh we want to produce
a message. So from CLI itself we can do
this. Okay you don't need uh spring boot
application itself to do uh producer
stuff. So this is what you will get
inside a bin.
Another important uh folder is config.
So within this if you open this part
apart from bin if you open this config
you will see so many dot properties.
Okay. So this folder is important for us
as it contains all the configuration for
our controller and broker node. So if
you just see carefully you have
broker.properties.
So this is just a default template for
broker node. Okay, let's say we have a
broker, right? Broker controller. So, it
has provided us some default properties.
Okay, consumer.property is for consumer.
Controller.property is for controller
node. So, here we have
server.properties. So, there are certain
nodes which act as a both broker plus
controller. So, this server.properties
is for both. And remember when I'm
saying it is just a default template.
Okay, you can say that you can reuse it
but these are just I would say the
default template. Always define your
own.
So
this folder is important. We will come
to that when we will create our own
config. Okay. Other folders like lips it
just contain the Kafka jar files and
their dependency. So this bin dot script
files use the code right those codes
present inside lib and there would be
log folder like whenever you will uh
initiate any server. So info warn error
message goes inside this folder. Okay.
So once you download the Kafka you will
get this folders and these two folders
would be important for us.
Step three, we need to write the
configuration for our controllers. Okay.
And where we have to put this
dotproperties configuration uh into
/config folder the one which I show you
inside this we have to put this.
So in what in our Kafka cluster what we
are doing is we are creating two broker
broker one broker two and controller one
controller two. So we are creating
dedicated dedicated controller. Okay,
that's what in production also happens.
Okay, we are not creating one node which
has both broker plus controller job. No,
we have a dedicated to broker to
controller. So I am writing one
controller one.properties.
Okay, so this is the property
application uh configuration
1.properties properties and these are
the config which I have said. So I will
tell you one by one the purpose of each
one.
So controller 1.properties controller
2.properties almost very much similar
and where they would stay inside /config
folder. Now let's see what all the
configs we have to add.
So first is process.
what role this node will perform whether
it act as a controller whether it act as
a broker or both. Okay. So if it only
act as a controller put controller if
only act as a broker only broker if both
put controller broker. Okay. So since we
are doing dedicated controller that's
why only controller I have put
each node in a cluster has a unique node
ID. So that's where I have given one.
Okay. Then we have listener
controller and the port number. What is
this listener? So this is nothing
internally it might be creating a socket
server [snorts] socket and this port
number it might be opening where it will
accept a TCP connection. Okay. So
listener list of port which are running
on this node. So this node it might have
opened multiple ports for doing certain
certain task. Okay. So internally
what it might be doing is new server
socket and the port number. So it will
open one TCP socket which is waiting for
connection. Nothing else very basic.
Okay. So you can we can open multiple
ports on this node. This is just an
example like you can open one and each
socket which is opening you can give one
label name or you can give some label or
name. So let's say 9093
the socket you are giving a name
controller.
So this socket I'm giving the name
controller. Okay, so like this you can
have multiple sockets open on this node
and for each socket you can provide one
logical name.
Okay, this logical name has a very big
importance.
I will show you as soon as we proceed
further. Okay, because they need to be
matched. Okay, so we'll show you. I will
not go into that. It will create
confusion. will go slowly. At this point
of time you need to understand that
purpose of this is that on this node
this port number would get open. Okay.
And this name I have given controller
controller.lister.names.
What does it mean? This means that which
listener
has to be used while it need to do
controller to controller communication.
You know that
multiple controllers stay in touch with
each other like follower leader right
they share their uh cluster metadata
info okay so you might have multiple
you might have multiple listeners
multiple port numbers this one this one
you can have many
so this node will use which listener to
connect with the other controller so
that's what this says that
hey use the control this name port
number which has this name controller.
So it will use this port to connect with
other controller. That's what it means.
This tell among all the listeners
defined use the one with name controller
for controller to controller
communication.
Clear?
Then we have controller.quaram.voters
voters like in a controller all the
controller nodes you can say if you
remember from the architecture video I
told you that each controller maintain a
static list of other controllers right
and this is the place where they
maintain a list of all the
controllers so one is nothing but a node
node ID at the rate IP and port number
Okay.
So this is the second so my second
controller and uh which node ID is two
that's why two at the rate and it is
running on port 9193 9193 I have used
okay so both both maintain both
controller maintain this list
similarly what is a security protocol
listener.security.protocol.map protocol
dom. So what security protocol your each
listener has to follow. Okay. So let's
say this port number this listener which
is tagged a name controller it should
follow plain text. Okay. So plain text
means no encryption no authentication
nothing. Okay. So there is one more SSL.
So there is one more like SSL which
means TLS encryption is required which
is used in production. Plain text you
can say that generally used for local
and development for testing purpose.
So what I am saying that when
controller controller communication
happens it should there should not be
any encryption used there should not be
any authentication happen. Okay, it
should happen in a plain text. That's
what you can have a comma separated
comma. If there are another controller,
let's say broker, broker, you can say
that SSL. Okay. So, it's a comma
separated. So, currently we have a
dedicated controller. It has only one
listener, one port. Okay. And that port
we have given a label controller. So,
that's what we are saying that this
listener should follow this security
protocol plain text.
Then we have log dot directory diir. So
this is the folder you can say that
where all the files for this node will
get persisted this path. Okay.
And then we have default partition num
uh default topic partition num
do.artition 3 and the replication factor
two. from the previous architecture
video. I hope you already know what is
partitions and what is replication
factor means. Okay. So if you also
remember from previous video I told you
the controller is the one that decide
okay this topic how many partition
who become the leader which top uh which
broker become the leader which broker
become the follower and what should be
the replication factor that is all
decided by controller. So controller has
this information present while creating
of a topic if you don't specify the
partition this default would be used.
So if you see the controller 2 also has
almost same thing. So this controller 2
should process.rol is controller node ID
I have changed it. Okay. And the port
number is running on 91 93. Okay. And uh
the name I have remember this this I
have kept same in both okay this has
importance when we will go with the
broker right you will understand the
importance why it need to be same okay
so controller.lister Listener name. Yes,
this is the listener need to be used to
connect to controller to controller
communication. It also maintain a static
list of all the controllers
and uh security protocol for the
controller display text and they also
should match otherwise one is SSL and
another is plain text then also it's a
problem. Okay. And its directory is
/temp/controller
2 - log. So this is its path. controller
one hyphen log is this path number of
partition default replication factor we
have defined okay
this number of partition default
replication factor could be different in
both the controller and whichever
controller become the leader they will
follow their own default okay
so these are the configuration for the
controllers
which we have to put under /config
folder
clear
the same thing I have specified
everything here
okay so offset replication factor
doesn't comes into the controller
it goes into
broker part okay if you remember from
the architecture video the consumer
related information
is handled by a broker not controller.
So here I have mentioned in this one
right uh controller
offset replication factor this comes
under broker. Okay. So we'll see when we
will uh see the configuration of the
broker.
So step four write the configuration for
brokers. So again this configuration
where we need to put /config folder. So
broker one.properties I am writing which
I will put under /config only.
Now here if you see process dot role I
want a dedicated broker only no combined
roles so only broker node id since I
every cluster each node is unique ID so
I have given three one or two is used
for controller one controller two
now here if you see controller quum
motors so each broker also maintains a
static list of the controllers
okay
Controller also kept this information.
Brocker also kept this information.
In architecture we topic I have already
told you why.
Now listener this broker which we are
creating broker one property is open
which port. So it has created this port
9092 where it would be listening for the
connection and you know that who connect
with broker producer and consumer. So
generally this port would be used by
producer consumer to connect with the
broker
advertise listener. So in the advertise
listener
what this means advertise listener. So
broker can open multiple listener.
Okay multiple port number here. Okay.
But
which port number it need to pass to
controller. So here understand the flow
here. Understand the flow in this part.
Okay.
Now uh let's say we have a broker. It
has
port one address one. You can say that
address one. It also has address IP
address two port two multiple. So now
they all pass this information to
controller.
Okay, controller maintain a
cluster metadata.
Now let's say producer
need to publish to let's say topic a
partition zero. What it will do? It will
first ask any broker let's say broker
one, broker two, broker three. It will
ask any broker, hey pass me the
metadata. Broker goes to the active
controller. Active controller fetch this
cluster metadata. Cluster metadata has
this information that okay for topic a
partition zero leader is broker one and
also it has information that broker one
you can connect with. This is the IP
address. This is the port. So this IP
and port who provides to the controller
broker only through advertise listener.
So it is just saying that hey controller
store this my information I'm listening
here.
Okay. So store this information in your
cluster metadata. It might have multiple
listeners but it pass this to the
controller.
Then we have enter.broker.lister
name. So this listener would be used
to
connect with different broker.
Understand this better again. So see
broker is doing two things.
Broker is connecting with producer,
broker is connecting with consumer.
Okay.
Broker also get in sync with another
broker
because one is leader another is
follower for certain partition. So
follower keep on fetching the
information from the leader. Okay.
Currently in our configuration we have
opened only one port 9092.
Okay. So the same listener the same port
we are using it for producer consumer
and for the broker also. Okay. So we are
saying that hey producer consumer all
clients should use 9092 to connect with
me and also we are saying that hey enter
dot broker dot listener.name name use
broker only this one only even the
multiple brokers can connect with the
same on the same port only same listener
you can also change that hey you can
give external
and call it internal
so you can create let's say two listener
you can change the name external and you
can create one more internal let's say
9098 something And uh you can say that
inter dot broker.lister name use the
listener inter internal use this
internal one. Okay. So means for
producer consumer it will use one uh
different listener and for brokers they
will use different listener. For
simplicity right or to better
understanding
I have opened only one port on this node
on this broker and the same would be
used by the producer consumer and the
same would be used by the broker to sync
each other.
Then we have controller.lister.name.
Now if you remember from the controller
I told you
why all the controllers which you are
creating has the same name either see
you can choose any name I have put
controller you can put anything let's
say C1 controller one or just C okay but
here the name should be same CC like
this okay why why they have to keep the
same name because in broker
You have to provide this name. If you
have multiple name, let's say controller
one you have name C1. Uh this is the
listener. For controller two, you have
the name C2. This is the listener. What
one will you will provide here? You can
only provide you can say that for
controller.
Okay, use this listener. So what exactly
happen internally?
So if you open the cluster metadata
information I will show you also
this uh has information like this. Hey
for this controller I have a controller
ID and endpoints. This controller has so
many endpoints. Okay let's say
controller internal it has external so
many. Now let's say
it want to connect with active
controller and active controller it
knows that it it is with ID 1. Okay, it
in the cluster metadata information it
know that active controller is one and I
will show you everything. Now in the
cluster metadata it know that active
controller is one with ID 1. So it will
say that okay give me the data of ID
controller one. Now which endpoint it
will use to communicate with controller.
So it will pick the name controller this
name. So it will use this to connect
with. That's why for every let's say
controller ID2
okay endpoint it can have many endpoints
so but we can have a same name
controller
okay so that at broker we can have the
name and the same name it will use for
all the controller that okay whatever
the controller I am connecting to active
controller could be controller ID 1
could be controller ID
And they can have many endpoints, many
listeners. I only interested into
listener with this name controller.
Okay.
And the security protocol should also
match that. Hey, for controller use
plain text and for broker also use plain
text because see broker is connecting
with the controller also. Broker is
connecting with other broker also. Okay.
So here for controller use plain text
and for this listener broker I am also
using plain text. This is just a
security protocol similar what we have
seen in the controller
log directory where does the uh place
the logs will get persisted for this
broker inside this path /temp/broker 1
logs
okay and here I have provided the
default retention log retention hours 7
days so till 7 days the data would be
present so you know that uh the data is
stored in segment forms. I have already
covered that in the architecture. So for
each segment you can say that it will
see the first event time. If that is
older than 7 days, the whole segment
will get deleted. It never delete one
event, one event individually. No, the
whole segment will get deleted. Okay.
Similarly, each segment maximum size is
1GB. So no segment can reach more than 1
GB. So that we have defined is here. And
also I told you like broker is the one
that maintain the consumer offset. I
already explained what is consumer
offset. Okay. So its replication factor
you know that default partition is 50
already. Okay. But how many replication
factor we can provide here two
you can change it also.
So understood the broker one properties.
Similarly I have set up a broker two
properties. Only difference is no node
ID is different.
And the port number which has opened
that is different.
Okay. And to the controller it also send
this 9192 port number. Rest is all I
have kept same.
So now we have configuration for
controller one, controller 2, broker
one, broker two. Okay. Currently all
these are individual configuration we
have set.
Now we need to add we need all these
four to be part of one cluster.
So that's the next part I am doing. So
till now here you can see that the same
thing controller one.properties
controller 2.properties same thing
broker 1.properties broker 2.properties
all I have put under this if you see
configuration.
So here if you can see broker
1.properties broker two.properties
controller 1.properties properties
controller 2.properties properties I
have put it here. Okay, till here it's
done.
Now the next step we have to done is map
all these nodes whichever we have
created with one cluster. Okay. So again
now our script come into handy. So there
is one script present inside a bin
kafka- storage.sh.
Okay. And you can say that this is the
subcomand random uuid.
So we can run this script and let me
also show you
doing that. So let me first stop the
controller one. Controller 2 is also
stopped.
Let's say it is stopping. [snorts]
Yeah. Clear.
Clear. Okay. So both controllers I have
stopped. Both brokers are also stopped.
Seems. Now first thing I have to done is
I have already done the setup. So first
I need to so servers are stopped but
their memory their files are already pro
persisted. So let me remove those files.
So we can do uh rm - rf and for each one
I have temp
for each one I have given like
controller one - locks
correct. So
let's remove that. Similarly, controller
2.Locks remove it. So you can say that I
am removing their memory. So we will
start fresh. Broker one hyphen locks
remove it. Broker 2 hyphen locks remove
it. Everything is removed. So now we
will start fresh.
So first thing is we need to generate a
cluster ID. So this is the command to
generate a cluster ID. So let's use
that.
So one cluster ID is generated. Now all
the four nodes which we have created
controller one, controller two, broker
one, broker two, we have to attach this
cluster ID with them. So that's what we
do. So this is the script kafka-
storage.sh. Now format is the subcomand
we are using and we are going to attach
this whatever the cluster ID we have got
we're going to attach it with
controller properties controller two
properties broker one properties broker
two properties
okay so let's do that
okay So controller one has run.
Now let me do for controller
2.properties.
Now let me do for
broker 1.properties
and let me attach this cluster ID with
broker 2.properties.
So I have run this command for all. So
now if you see this folder
within the temp and all the controller
one controller 2 you will see
meta.properties will get added. Okay in
the meta.properties
you will see that controller one right
controller one node ID is one it attach
with this cluster ID which we have
created.
[snorts] Okay. Similarly it would be
added for all. We can do that like we
can go to the folder.
We can go to the first controller one
meta.properties. You can open it. This
is the cluster ID we added attached with
node ID 1. Similarly, it would be there
for let's open uh broker.
Let's say broker 2
- logs.
It also has meta.properties
cluster ID node ID 4. Okay. So now what
we have done is we have attach attached
one cluster ID with all our four nodes
configuration.
This step is also done. Now step six we
need to start all the node server. So
first we have to start the controller
and then we need to start the broker
because broker when started they will
try to call the controller to load the
cluster metadata. So for that clust
controller need to be up and running. So
we will start our controller one and
controller two first. So this is the
script I am using Kafka server start.sh
and we need this is the subcomand where
we need to pass the property path. So we
can run this.
So here let me clear it up. And this is
where I will run controller one
properties. This is where I will run
controller 2.properties.
[snorts]
Let me start it.
Let's start controller one.properties.
Let's start controller
two. properties.
So this one is started.
This one is also started.
Okay.
So now here if you see let's go inside
controller. Now one thing if you
remember from the architecture video
when there are more than one controller
one has to be leader another has to be
follower. So who become a leader and
follower that also we can know that.
Let's go to any of the controller.
Let's go to controller
to logs. Okay, you can go to any because
uh the cluster metadata is synced
between two. So here if you see cluster
metadata is created and they have a
quorum state. So if you open that quorum
state, who is the leader with id one?
Okay. So this information we can know
that for each controller you can check
the quarum state and you can see that
who is the leader. So this information
is persisted. Our controller one
controller 2 is up and leader is
selected.
Okay. Now we have to start the broker
one and broker two. The same thing Kafka
- server start.sh and the broker
1.properties.
So here I am running my
broker one
and here I will run
broker 2.properties.
Okay. So here let's run the broker one.
Here let's run the broker two.
Kafka server started node ID 3. Kafka
server started node ID 4.
Okay. So both the broker started.
So till now what we have done is
we have created a cluster with ID. Okay.
And we have created two broker two
controller and each associated with this
cluster only.
Okay. And we have started the server for
all. Now we need to check the cluster
status. So the same thing you can run
this command.
The script we need to use is Kafka -
metadata quorum. SS. See we don't have
to memorize this command. Okay. It just
like we can look out for it over the
internet like okay which script I need
to use to check this status. But only
thing is if if we are clear what we are
doing. Okay. So now here if you see if
you run this this get a status that
leader who is the leader of the
controller with ID1 or controller one
current voters. So it should have two
controllers. So this ID1 and ID2 these
are the two controller and current
observer should have the list of all the
brokers. So four and three are the
brokers.
So this is and they are all part of this
cluster ID. So this is our cluster is
setup done. Okay. So we are able to set
up this and yes bootstrap controller is
you see we are running a CLI. If you
remember from the architecture video no
matter whether from CLI or from producer
you can't directly talk with controller
it has to be passed through broker and
when you have multiple broker just
invoke any broker and they will pass it
to the controller so that's why just
bootstrap controller is like any broker
you can pass the address
so [snorts]
our setup is completed now we can test
the producer consumer consumer using a
script. So today I will not uh set up a
application for producer and application
for consumer. So we will test through
script. So now you can see that script
is now helpful uh when you don't have a
complete application up and running. So
directly script we can run. So now I am
first creating a sample topic to test.
Okay. So which script file we are using
is Kafka - topic.sh SH
bootstrap server like we need to we
can't directly talk to controller to
create a topic. So we have to call any
broker. Okay. So that's why bootstrap
server anything hyphen. So this is a
command hyphen create hyphen topic. What
is a topic name? Okay. So let's create
run this command. You can say that we
want to create this topic.
Create a topic order event topic. So now
our topic is created.
So we can check the status of the topic
now here and the sub command I'm using
is hyphen describe.
So see this one.
So what we have set three partition okay
and two replication factor
that's what we have right. So here we
have partition zero, partition 1,
partition two. Okay. And the replication
factor is 2
4 3 3 4 4 3. And this is the ISR. We
already have seen what is ISR.
So
clear like we are able to create a
topic. Now
so nums do.artition I have given three
and during topic creation I haven't
defined how many partition we need to
create. Okay during create I haven't
create. So that's why it create three
partition by default and two replication
factor by default. And we have checked
the status also that for each partition
who is the leader. Partition zero leader
is four. Partition one leader is three.
Partition two leader is four. And these
are the replica factors.
Now topic is created. We need to test
the producer. So we are using a script
kafka console producer.sh
connect with any broker at start. Okay.
because it doesn't know. So currently we
also we haven't provided any key. It
might be like whatever the algorithm
which we have discussed. Okay, it
doesn't know whatever the partition come
whether it's a leader who is the leader
or not. It just ask any broker let's say
for now.
Okay. And uh generally what happen is it
will get a metadata internally has a lot
of logic that it get a metadata
information and from that metadata
information it select who is the leader
and then
push a publish request we have so again
I'm saying the prerequisite video for
this is the architecture one then only
you would be able to clearly understand
what internally might be happening. So
let's say this is a producer
command I'm running.
Now we can publish events like
hello this is shange
how are you like this I am publishing
events okay and now we need to do
consumer test the same thing kafka
console consumer.cript script okay and
which topic it need to read is this and
from where from beginning
so if you from the consumer let's say if
I'm running this
[snorts]
see hello this is shash how are you
whatever we have published here it able
to read it
so today our agenda is not to set up
consumer not to set up produc producer.
Our agenda is to set up cluster that we
have done
this. We have set up the cluster. Now we
will set up the producer through
application not through CLI. We will
also set up consumer through application
not through CLI. And then we will
connect with this cluster. Okay. And how
this cluster internally working? I hope
now it should be clear.
Okay,
any doubt let me know. We can discuss
into the comment section. But yes, we
are able to
uh make our Kafka cluster up and
running.
Okay guys, thank you. Bye.